Disaster Awakening Chapter
Part Four
The Great Hinamizawa Disaster
saa, wasuremashou sono mirai ga
Come, let us forget about the future...
Planning
Takeshi Oikawa
Akihiro Kawamura
Akihiro Yuasa
Original Work ・ Original Story/Supervision
Ryukishi07/07th Expansion
"Higurashi no Naku Koro ni"
"Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai"
mata chinurarete yuku nante
...ending up stained in blood again.
Series Composition
Toshifumi Kawase
Character Design
Overall Animation Supervisor
Kyuuta Sakai
Art Director
Chikako Shibata
Color Design
Shinji Matsumoto
namanurui kaze toguromaitara
If the soft wind coils up...
Camera Director
Masayuki Kawaguchi
Editing
Masahiro Matsumura
Music
Kenji Kawai
Sound Director
Hozumi Gouda
sore ga tabun aizu
...that is probably a sign.
nukedashitete
Break free.
Opening Theme
"Naraku no Hana"
(Flower in Hell)
Vocals
Lyrics
Composition
Arrangement
Eiko Shimamiya
Tomoyuki Nakazawa
Takeshi Ozaki
kanashisugiru unmei kara
From your heart-wrenching fate.
Music Producer
Music Production
Akira Yoshikawa
Frontier Works
anata wa naraku no hana ja nai
You are not a flower in hell.
Producers
Mika Nomura
Hiroyuki Oomori
Takeshi Okamura
sonna basho de sakanaide
Don't blossom in such a place.
Animation Producer
Animation Production
Kouji Iijima
Studio Deen
sakanaide
Don't blossom there.
karametorarete ikanaide
Don't get entangled.
oto mo naku tobikau toki no kakera
Fragments of time flutter about without a sound.
Production
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai Production Committee
Director
Chiaki Kon
Hi
gu
ra
shi
no
Na
ku
Koro
ni
Kai
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai
（沙都子(さとこ)）梨花(りか)　やっぱり…
Rika...
So it was true...
（梨花）あなたには何もできない
There is nothing you can do.
（梨花）もう間に合わない
It is already too late.
No one believes me.
（沙都子）誰も信じてくれない
でも 絶対に何かがおかしいのに
But something is definitely off.
どうしたらいいの？　にーにー
What should I do, Nii-nii...
（沙都子）
一体 誰？　何のために？　私(わたくし)を？
Just who is it?
For what reason would he be after me?
Or...
それとも…　梨花を？
...could Rika be his target?
I'm afraid...
（梨花）怖い…
（沙都子）ハッ
（梨花）
もう止められないわ きっと
I'm sure I can't stop it anymore...
（沙都子）私だけじゃない
梨花も ずっとおびえてた
It wasn't just me.
Rika has been frightened all along.
I'll just have to protect Rika.
私が梨花を守るしかない
（熊谷(くまがい)）
はい　死因は睡眠薬による中毒死
Yes.
The cause of death is narcotic poisoning.
暴行の跡や不審な点はないため
ほぼ自殺と見られます
Since there are no traces of assault...
...we assume it was a suicide.
（大石(おおいし)）自殺？　あの入江(いりえ)先生が？
Suicide!?
Dr. Irie committed suicide?
そんな…
No way...
Hey you!
（熊谷）
そこ　子供は帰った 帰った！
Children don't belong here!
私 入江先生と
約束していたんですの
I had an appointment with Dr. Irie!
約束？
（沙都子）はい
An appointment?
Yes!
相談したいことがありまして
今朝早くに連絡したら―
I wanted to consult him about something...
When I called him early this morning...
“いつでもいいから
いらっしゃい”って…
...he said I could come over anytime...
相談したいことって
ちなみに どんなこと？
The thing you wanted to consult him about...
...what was it, if I may ask?
W-Well...
そ… それが
おい　何やってるんだ？
Hey!
What are you doing there?
あ…　いつの間にか
眠ってしまいましたわ
When did I doze off...
もう12時…
It's already midnight...
Weren't those policemen supposed to come?
お巡りさんが来てくれる約束じゃ
ありませんでしたっけ？
Rika...
（沙都子）梨花
Rika!
梨花　梨花 起きて　梨花！
Rika, wake up!
Rika!
（梨花）ん…
（沙都子）梨花　誰か来ますわ！
Rika!
Someone's here!
早く！　え…？
Hurry!
Quickly!
（梨花）早く
隠れて
Hide in here.
あ…　梨花？
Rika!
（梨花）私はいいの
Don't worry about me.
何言ってるんですの!?　早く！
What are you talking about!?
Hurry!
あいつらの狙いは私
あなたは隠れていて
They're after me.
You keep hiding!
Don't come out no matter what happens!
何があっても出てこないで
（沙都子）何言ってるんですの？
さあ 早く！
What are you saying!?
Come on, hurry!
Rika!
梨花！
大丈夫なのです
Don't worry.
（梨花）
また すぐに会えるのですから
We will meet again soon.
（男）覆え
Hey.
り… 梨花！
Rika!
Don't let her run.
（男）逃がすな
（沙都子）梨花…　うう…
Rika...
梨花～！
Rika!
梨花？
Rika?
Rika!
梨花！
梨花　どこなの？　梨花！
Rika?
Where are you, Rika!?
きゃああー！
うあ…　梨花…
Rika...
痛っ　うう…
くうっ…
うう…　助けて
Help me...
誰か助けて
Someone...
...help me!
（沙都子）一体 なんでこんな…
Just why...
...is this happening...
（自衛隊員）
雛見沢(ひなみざわ)への道を完全封鎖
Barricade all roads leading to Hinamizawa.
報道関係の車両も
通さないよう願います
Do not let any press vehicles through.
救急車は
自衛隊の指示に従うように
Ambulances are to follow the Self-Defense Force's orders.
I repeat.
繰り返します
雛見沢への道を完全封鎖…
Barricade all roads leading to Hinamizawa.
梨花…
Rika...
何ですの…!?
What...
...on earth...
いやあー！
（自衛隊員）うん？
No!!!
（自衛隊員）
生存者が！　生存者がいたぞー！
A survivor!
There's a survivor!
（自衛隊員）なに!?
What!?
（自衛隊員）大丈夫か!?
（自衛隊員）子供だ！
Are you all right!?
It's a child!
（自衛隊員）
救護班だ！　救護班を呼べ！
The rescue squad!
Call the rescue squad!
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni
Kai
Yesterday at midnight...
（アナウンサー）昨日の深夜
人口2000人の雛見沢地区に―
...toxic volcanic gases erupted in the Hinamizawa district with a population of 2,000.
火山性の有毒ガスが発生しました
災害は 雛見沢全戸に
及んでいる模様で―
The disaster is reported to have befallen the entirety of Hinamizawa...
...and according to a publication by the SDF engaged in rescue operations at the scene...
現地で救助に当たっている
自衛隊の発表では―
...the victim count is expected to reach two thousand.
犠牲者は2000人に及ぶものと
見られています
At present, the only confirmed survivor is one Satoko Houjou-san.
現在のところ
生存が確認されているのは―
北条(ほうじょう)沙都子さん１名のみで―
She has been admitted to a hospital in the area.
同地区の病院に
収容されているとのことです
Consultation Room 3
（大石）どういうことなんですか？
話ができないというのは
What do you mean she's incapable of speech?
She seems to have suffered a severe emotional shock.
（医者）精神的に かなりひどい
ショックを受けているようで―
That shock has caused her mind to shut down...
そのショックで
心を閉ざしてしまい―
...temporarily disabling her.
一時的に廃人のようになり
何を話しかけても 答えるどころか
She's in a state where she's not only unable to answer...
反応もしない状態に
なってしまっているんです
...she won't even react to anything you say to her.
Since you say it's temporary...
一時的にというと
回復の見込みはあるわけですよね？
...you expect her to recover, right?
Around when will that be?
それは いつ頃？
うう　何とも…
I can't say...
何ともって あなた医者でしょ
You can't say!?
Aren't you a doctor!?
This is up to her own strength.
（医者）こういうことは
本人の力次第なんですよ
Her own strength...
本人の力？
はい　心の力とでも言いますか…
Yes.
The strength of her mind, you could say.
う～ん　そうですか
Is that so...
う～ん　参りましたねえ
I'm a bit at a loss here...
I came because I had a lot to ask you...
唯一 雛見沢大災害を
生き残った あなたに―
...the sole survivor of the Great Hinamizawa Disaster.
あの日のことを いろいろと
お聞きしたいと思って来たんですが
ハア…
Well, just listen to me then.
まあ 聞くだけ聞いてください
勝手にしゃべりますから
I'll do the talking myself.
Thing is...
実はね こんな物を見つけましてね
...we found this.
Do you recall seeing this hat?
この帽子 見覚えはありませんか？
Look over here.
ほら ここにね
刺繍(ししゅう)で名前が書かれているんですが
A name is embroidered here.
It says Ryuguu.
“竜宮(りゅうぐう)”って書いてあるんですよ
Indeed.
そう
It appears to be your friend Rena Ryuuguu's hat.
あなたのお友達の竜宮レナさんの
帽子だと思われるんですがね
See these red stains?
ここに赤いシミがあるでしょう？
これ 血なんですよ
It's blood.
Blood of the same type as Rena-san's.
それも レナさんと同じ血液型のね
But here is what's odd about it.
妙なのは ここからなんですがね
This hat was found in the mountains a short distance from the Great Hinamizawa Disaster...
この帽子が見つかったのが
雛見沢大災害…
つまり 火山性ガスが
流出した地域から―
...that is, away from the area that was wiped out by volcanic gases.
ちょっと離れた山の中なんですよ
An SDF investigation squad found it and delivered it to us.
自衛隊の捜索の方が見つけましてね
届けてくれたんです
However...
ですが どうも私には分からない
...I just don't understand.
なぜ そんな所に―
What was Rena-san's blood-stained hat doing in such a place?
血の付いた
レナさんの帽子が落ちていたのか
ああ ちなみにレナさんの遺体も
出ていないんですよ
By the way, Rena-san's body wasn't found.
It was late at night when the disaster occurred.
災害が起きたのは深夜遅くです
Why was she all the way out in the mountains that late?
あの人 どうしてそんな遅くに―
山の中に
出かけていたんでしょうかねえ
Why did we only find her beloved hat in the mountains?
なぜ 愛用の帽子だけが
山の中に落ちていたんでしょう？
You know...
私はねえ この帽子
...I'm thinking this hat might be a message from Rena-san.
レナさんからのメッセージでは
ないかと考えているんです
That disaster wasn't actually a gas disaster...
あの災害
実はガス災害なんかじゃなく―
もっと何か他の事故か
あるいは事件で―
...but some other accident or incident...
Perhaps Rena-san learned of that...
それを知ってしまった
レナさんは―
...and fled the village in an attempt to let someone know.
そのことを誰かに伝えようとして
村を逃れたのでは？
Actually, it wasn't just Rena-san.
実は レナさんだけじゃない
Around twenty people have been reported missing.
20人ほどの方が
行方不明扱いになっているんです
It was a disaster at midnight.
深夜の大災害ですよ？
When a disaster occurs past bedtime...
就寝中の災害で
ほとんどの人が―
自宅の寝室で
お亡くなりになっているのに
...almost everyone passes away while sleeping in their bedrooms.
Yet their bodies were missing.
なのに遺体がない
なぜか帽子は山の中
And this hat somehow turned up in the mountains.
Just what is the reason for all this?
こりゃ どういうわけですかねえ
アッハッハッハ
This was no natural disaster!
これは自然災害なんかじゃない！
What on earth happened in Hinamizawa that night...
あの夜 雛見沢で一体 何が？
Just what the hell did you see!?
あんたは一体 何を見たんだ!?
ハア…　と いうようなことをね
Well, that kind of stuff...
...is what I came here to ask you about.
あなたにお尋ねしたくて
来たんですが
Looks like that's impossible right now.
どうやら 今は無理のようですな
Is something wrong?
（看護師）どうかしましたか？
ああ いやあ 別に
No, it's nothing...
I'll come again.
また来ますよ　もう１つの事件―
There was one other incident.
古手(ふるで)梨花さんの
惨殺事件のほうでも―
I still have a plethora of questions to ask regarding the brutal murder of Rika Furude.
お聞きしたいことが
山ほどありますので
い… 今 眉が動いたようですが
I'm pretty sure her eyebrows moved just now!
A bodily reaction.
（看護師）生体反応です
It's not like she regained consciousness.
意識を取り戻したわけじゃ
ないですよ
う…　そうですか
Is that so...
Well, if something comes to mind please tell me...
まあ 何か思い出したら
教えてください 北条さん
...Houjou-san.
Goodbye.
（大石）どうも
Now Hinamizawa's chain of mystery murders will remain unsolved too, huh...
（大石）これで
雛見沢連続怪死事件も闇の中か
[Okinomiya Police Station]
Understood.
（小宮山(こみやま)）
分かりました　はい　はい
Yes...
Yes.
Understood.
分かりました　どうも
（ドアが開く音）
Goodbye.
あ 大石さん
どこ行ってたんですか？
Ooishi-san!
Where did you go?
ああ ちょっと やぼ用です　何か？
Some minor business.
Anything new?
（小宮山）いえ 熊谷(くまがい)さん
まだ連絡が取れないんですよ
No...
Kumagai-san still hasn't contacted us.
Kuma-chan hasn't?
熊ちゃんが？
（小宮山）はい
課長が気にしちゃってて
Yeah...
Chief was worried about it...
I'm going to go look around for him.
ちょっと心当たりを
捜してきますんで
後 よろしくお願いします
Please take care of things here.
Is that so...
そうですか
あ…　ああ ちょっと
Wait!
ん…　はい？
Yes?
Didn't Kuma-chan say anything before he disappeared?
（大石）熊ちゃん いなくなる前に
何か言ってませんでしたっけ？
いえ
No...
ふむ…
あっ　そういえば熊谷さん
Now that you mention it...
...I believe he had some business at the local police station regarding Rika Furude.
確か 古手梨花のことで
地元の派出所に用があるって
それで 僕ら別れたんですが
That's when we separated...
古手梨花？
Rika Furude?
I'll come again.
また来ますよ　もう１つの事件―
There was one other incident.
I still have a plethora of questions to ask regarding the brutal murder of Rika Furude.
古手梨花さんの
惨殺事件のほうでも―
お聞きしたいことが
山ほどありますので
Hey!
おい！　確か
古手梨花と北条沙都子は―
Rika Furude and Satoko Houjou were living in the same house, right?
同じ家に住んでいたんだよな？
Yeah...
ええ　２人とも
両親がいないってことで…
Since they both lost their parents.
Why didn't I realize that sooner!?
なんで そんなことに
気づかなかったんだ
え？
（大石）北条沙都子が見たのは―
What Satoko Houjou witnessed...
雛見沢大災害のほうじゃない
...wasn't the Great Hinamizawa Disaster!
古手梨花惨殺事件の
ほうだったんだ！
It was Rika Furude's brutal murder!
（小宮山）ええ!?
（大石）行くぞ！
Let's move!
（小宮山）えっ
（大石）車を回せ！
Bring out the car!
（小宮山）は… はい！
Y-Yes sir!
Shouldn't we go look for Kumagai-san...?
いいんですかねえ？
熊谷さん 捜しに行かなくて
構わん　そっちは後回しだ　急げ
No!
That can wait.
Hurry up!
（小宮山）は… はい！
Y-Yes sir!
Thing is...
実はね こんな物を見つけましてね
...we found this.
You know...
私はね この帽子―
...I'm thinking this hat might be a message from Rena-san.
レナさんからのメッセージでは
ないかと考えているんです
This was no natural disaster!
これは自然災害なんかじゃない！
What on earth happened in Hinamizawa that night...
あの夜 雛見沢で一体 何が？
Just what the hell did you see!?
あんたは一体 何を見たんだ!?
きゃああー！
I know!
分かった
I understand now!
分かりましたわ
Rena-san's message...
レナさんのメッセージ
Akio Naka
Saisuke Yoshida
Hitomi Toyonaga
Makoto Suzuki
Daisuke Nishi
Gaku Eda
Daisuke Shibutani
Yuuki Fujita
Satoko Houjou
Akio Naka
Akio
Sai
Hitomi Toyonaga
フン
（大石）えいっ
At 1:32 a.m...
（医者）午前１時32分
お亡くなりになりました
...she passed away.
ど… どうして？
W-Why!?
Her condition suddenly worsened.
（医者）急に容体が悪化しまして…
急性心不全と思われます
It appears to have been acute heart failure.
That can't be...
そんな…
Why would she have a heart failure!?
なんで心不全なんかに!?
We can't say for sure without an inspection...
（医者）検視してみないと
確かなことは言えませんが―
...but the symptoms suggest acute heart failure.
症状は急性心不全です
There's no way!
バカな！　そんなバカな！
That's ridiculous!
You're fucking kidding me!
ふざけるなあ！　ううっ…
Cast
Rena Ryuuguu
Satoko Houjou
Rika Furude
Mai Nakahara
Mika Kanai
Yukari Tamura
anata no nakigara ni tsuchi wo kakeru
I cover your corpse with soil...
Cast
Kuraudo Ooishi
Komiyama
SDF Member
Doctor
Anchorman
Nurse
Chafuurin
Satoshi Tsuruoka
Gen Nakano
Daisuke Matsuoka
Katsuhiro Oota
Akane Tomonaga
sore ga kinjirareteita toshitemo
...even though that may have been forbidden.
junsui na manazashi no kairaku ni wa
There was a temptation you could not hide...
kakushikirenai yuuwaku ga atta
...in your pure, blissful eyes.
doushite tsumi ga aru no darou
Why does sin exist?
Ending Theme
"Taishou a"
(Target a)
Vocals
Lyrics
Composition/
Arrangement
doushite batsu ga aru no darou
Why does punishment exist?
hori no saki wa amari ni mo shiroku
That blindingly white end of the canal...
mugen ni tsuzuku yami wo sasotta
...invited the infinite darkness.
Scenario
Toshifumi Kawase
Storyboards
Episode Direction
Sanjin Tomo
Yuuji Satoru
nani mo kamo ga azayaka ni miete
I can see everything clearly now.
Animation Supervisor
Minefumi Harada
sugu ni kieteshimau
It will soon vanish.
Animation Production
Studio Deen
Production
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai Production Committee
© 2007 Ryukishi07/Hinamizawa Three Great Houses
People in Hinamizawa speak with quite a heavy dialect.
（梨花）雛見沢って
結構 なまりが強いのです
That's true.
（羽入(はにゅう)）そうですねえ
Since there isn't much contact with the outside world...
外部との交流が少ないので―
...there seem to be a few atypical words in use.
独自の言い回しが
あるみたいなのです
"To nipper" is one of them.
（梨花）“にぱる”も
その１つなのです
Exactly!
（羽入）はいなのです
お年寄りが よく使いますのです
The elderly use the word a lot.
"In winter, we had little to do since we couldn't go outside due to heavy snowfall...
“冬の間は 大雪で外にも出られず
やることがなかったんで”
...so we just sat at home all day and nippered around."
“日がな一日 にぱっていたわ”
なのです
When I'm a little older...
（梨花）
ボクも もう少し大きくなったら
にぱりまくるのです
...I'll be nippering away too!
Next time, the Massacre Chapter, Part One.
次回　皆殺し編 其の壱
「迷路の法則」
"Rules of the Labyrinth."
にぱにぱにぱ～なのですう
Higurashi no Naku Koro ni Kai
Next time
Massacre Chapter
Part One
Rules of the Labyrinth